A Guide to the Papers of the Dean of Women, University of Virginia 1914-1969
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Dean of Women, University of Virginia, 1914-1969
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-34/1/1.701
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were transferred from the Office of the Dean of Women, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, to Special Collections on May 29, 1970.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of administrative records from the Dean of Women's Office at the University of Virginia, ca. 1,500 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet), 1914-1969, during the period before co-education at the University, and notes and note cards used for the typescript Women and the University by Mary E. Whitney, written in collaboration with Rebecca S. Wilburn in 1969.
Topics in the papers include the details about the construction and furnishing of the Mary Munford Dormitory for women; papers concerning the women's alumni association; two applications from black females for housing at the University (see folders 4 & 5 in Box 1); the lawsuit against the University to force the admission of women as undergraduates; details about the bequest from the Emily Clark Balch estate; material about the conversion of Mary Washington to a liberal arts college, 1944-1945; and women applicants to the University of Virginia as special students, just prior to full acceptance in 1970. There is a separate folder for specifications for Randall Hall by Stanislaw Makielski, which was used as a dormitory for nurses at one point in its long career.
In a folder of correspondence between President Colgate W. Darden, Jr. and the dean of women, Roberta Hollingsworth Gwathmey, Dean of Women, 1935-1967, they discuss the need for and the construction of a new dormitory to house women at the University of Virginia, the Mary Munford dormitory, which opened in 1952 (see 1947-1951), a controversy about The Virginia Reel publishing vulgar material (1950 March 24), and Anna J. Franklin, a black student in medicine (1955 March 7, April 7).
Also present is the research notes and note cards for the typescript, Women and the University by Mary E. Whitney, appointed to succeed Dean Gwathmey as the Dean of Women in 1967. A bound copy of the typescript is available in the public reference area in the reading room of Special Collections.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic on the folder heading.
Contents List
- Alumnae Association of the Women of the University of Virginia, 1940 May-1949 March (Box-folder 1:1)
  Correspondence
- Alumnae Association of the Women of the University of Virginia, 1940 May-1949 March (Box-folder 1:1a)
- Alumnae Association of the Women of the University of Virginia, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 1:2)
  Treasurer's Papers.
- Alumnae Association of the Women of the University of Virginia, 1946-1949, (index cards) (Box-folder 1:3)
  Treasurer's Papers. Membership Payments.
- Black Applicants for Housing, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Black Applicants for Housing, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 1:5)
  Mrs. Ruth W. Digg[e?]s
- Colgate W. Darden, Jr. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Regina Fisher Speech concerning Coeducation at the University of Virginia, 1942 (Box-folder 1:7)
  1920-1940
- Historical Material concerning Women at the University of Virginia, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Historical Material concerning Examinations for Women, 1942 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Historical Material concerning Objections to Proposed Co-ordinate Woman's College, 1914-1944 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Lawsuit concerning Mrs. Jo Anne Kirstein, et al. vs. Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia, et al., 1969 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Mary Munford Dormitory Construction, 1947 April-1949 September (Box-folder 1:12)
- Mary Munford Dormitory Construction (Box-folder 1:13)
- Mary Munford Dormitory Construction, 1949, 1951 (Box-folder 1:14)
  Architectural Drawings, First and Second Floor Plans and University of Virginia Master Plan (oversize).
- Mary Munford Dormitory, Estate of Emily Clark Balch, 1952-1967 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Mary Munford Dormitory, Marshal Field & Company Décor, 1951 January-May (Box-folder 2:2)
- Mary Munford Dormitory, Marshal Field & Company Décor, 1951 June-1959 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Mary Munford Dormitory, Women's Dormitory, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Mary Washington College, Committee on Conversion, 1944-1945, (1 of 2 folders) (Box-folder 2:5)
- Mary Washington College, Committee on Conversion, 1944-1945, (2 of 2 folders) (Box-folder 2:6)
- Mary Washington College -Conversion to a Liberal Arts College, 1945 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Photographs, including W.S.A. Officers, Nutter, Wiard, Tull, and Gilbert, 1950-1951, n.d. (Box-folder 2:8)
  Aerial view of the University of Virginia, central grounds; the West Range; and [women's?] dormitories.
- School of Education, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Specifications for Alterations and Additions for Randall Hall, UVA by Stanislaw J. Makielski, Architect, n.d. (Box-folder 3:1)
- Women Applicants as Special Students, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Women and the University, n.d., Notes (Box-folder 3:3)
  Before 1900, Chapter 1
- Women and the University, n.d., Notes (Box-folder 3:4)
  1900-1919, Chapter 2
- Women and the University, n.d., Notes (Box-folder 3:5)
  1920-1930, Chapter 3
- Women and the University, n.d., Notes (Box-folder 3:6)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4
- Women and the University, n.d., Notes (Box-folder 3:7)
  1968-1970, Chapter 5, Vote on Coeducation
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 3:8)
  1900-1919, Chapter 2 (1 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 3:9)
  1900-1919, Chapter 2 (2 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 3:10)
  1900-1919, Chapter 2 (3 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 3:11)
  1900-1919, Chapter 2 (4 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:1)
  1920-1930, Chapter 3 (1 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:2)
  1920-1930, Chapter 3 (2 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:3)
  1920-1930, Chapter 3 (3 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:4)
  1920-1930, Chapter 3 (4 of 4 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:5)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4 (1 of 6 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:6)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4 (2 of 6 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:7)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4 (3 of 6 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:8)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4 (4 of 6 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:9)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4 (5 of 6 envelopes)
- Women and the University, n.d., Note cards (Box-folder 4:10)
  1931-1950, Chapters 3 and 4 (6 of 6 envelopes)